Finding Aid for Student Activities and Leadership Office (University of Michigan) records, 1959-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Student Activities and Leadership Office (University of Michigan) records 1959-2008, 1994-1999
University of Michigan. Student Activities and Leadership Office, 1959-2008
3 linear feet
0748 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Student Activities and Leadership Office (SAL) is a resource designed to help students make the most of their co-curricular experience; developing effective student organizations and student leaders through training and education. This record group includes materials documenting oversight of many student leadership and service programs including the Michigan LeaderShape Program, the annual Student Recognition Awards, and the student organization the University Activities Center (UAC).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the University of Michigan Student Activities and Leadership Office (donor no. 9058 ) beginning in February 2007. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Student Activities and Leadership Office was originally part of the Student Organization and Activities and Programs (SOAP), a student services unit reporting to the Michigan Union and Student Services Offices. In the late 1980s, the unit refocused its mission to concentrate more on leadership development and education and, along with changing its mission, it changed its name to the Student Organization and Development Center (SODC). In the early 1990s, the creation of the Dean of Students office and the formation of a Co-Curricular Programs Unit sparked a large-scale reorganization of many university units, including the SODC. It was at this point that the unit renamed itself the Student Activities and Leadership Office and solidified its central mission to develop effective student organizations and leaders through training and education.
In order to fulfill this mission, SAL committed to organizing student organization fairs at events such as "Festifall" and homecoming, and expanded its leadership training programs. In particular, starting in 1993, they began offering twice-yearly LeaderShape seminars--intensive, dynamic six-day programs intended to develop students' conceptions of leadership and responsible citizenship. They also took on an advising role for large student organizations, taking on advisorial responsibilities for the University Activities Center and, in 1995, the Michigan Student Assembly. As part of their role of promoting leadership through student organizations and campus activities they also published directories of student organizations as well as guides for establishing and managing successful student organizations.
The University of Michigan Student Activities and Leadership (SAL) record group contains materials generating from affiliate organizations and offices dating from as early as 1959, but the bulk of the materials were generated in the mid 1990s and focus on the work the office has done as SAL. The record group consists of four series: Administrative Files, Program Files, Photographs, and Publications.
Subjects:
Student activities--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Student Activities and Leadership Office.; University of Michigan. Student Organization and Activities Program.; University of Michigan. Student Organization Development Center.; University of Michigan--Students.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files, 1982-2008 series (0.5 linear feet) contains general administrative files generated by the office and its executive director. Included in this is an organizational history file that contains valuable information about the office's history and its relationships with other university units. This series also contains annual reports, memos, correspondence, and end of term reports that provide valuable insight into the running of the office.
  - Annual Reports 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 2003-2005 (Box 1)
  - Director Correspondence 1994-1998, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - End of Term Reports 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - DIAG Usage Applications 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Internship Manual 1992, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - SAL Advisory Survey 2006 (Box 1)
  - SAL Organizational History 1991-1995 (Box 1)
  - SAL Policy Research 2000-2008 (Box 1)
  - SAL Sample Student Organization Forms 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - SOAP (Office of Student Organizations, Activities, and Programs Annual Reports, 1982-1984. (Box 1)
  - Student Affairs Programming Council (SAPC) 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- Program Files
  The Program Files, 1983-2006 series (1.5 linear feet) comprises the bulk of the collection and includes records relating to various programs run by, or otherwise under the aegis of, the Student Activities and Leadership office. Most notably, this series contain records relating to the Michigan LeaderShape program and its management and development on campus. It also includes information about other SAL run programs, including planning files and program evaluations and records of the University Activities Center, one of the student organizations under SAL's advisement.
  - DIAG Barbeque 2006 (Box 1)
  - Festifall 1993-2001, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Homecoming 1995 (Box 1)
  - Homecoming 1996 (Box 1)
  - SAL Leadership Conference 1995 (Box 1)
  - Leadership 2017, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Conference Evaluations (Box 1)
  - Leadership Conference Workshops (Box 1)
  - Leadership Connection 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Michigan LeaderShape 1995-1998, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan LeaderShape 1999, 2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan LeaderShape Board Meetings 1998 (Box 2)
  - Michigan LeaderShape Facilitator Training 1998 (Box 2)
  - Michigan LeaderShape Cluster Facilitator 2001 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Leadership Awards 1996-1999 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Leadership Initiatives (MIP) 1991-1998 scattered, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Leadership Initiatives (MIP) Saturn Awards 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Leadership Initiatives (MIP) Support 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Leadership Initiatives (MIP) Teamwork at U of M 1999 (Box 2)
  - Mission: Michigania 1999 (Box 2)
  - Project Community-Trained Volunteer Corps 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Project S.E.R.V.E. 1990 (Box 2)
  - Student Recognition Awards 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Synergy (Box 2)
  - Synergy Photographs (Box 2)
  - University Activities Center
    - General 1984-1992, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Annual Report 2002-2003 (Box 2)
    - Budgets 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Retreat 1998 (Box 2)
    - Ticket Central 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - Transition 1985 (Box 2)
  - Winterfest 1997 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs, 1996-2005 series (.25 linear feet) is composed of both candid and professional, posed photographs of SAL organized events. The bulk of these photographs are of LeaderShape participants.
  - LeaderShape Candids, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - LeaderShape Group Photos, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Publications
  The Publications, 1959-2009 series (.75 linear feet) contains numerous publications dealing with student organizations and leadership produced or collected by SAL. This series includes published guides and handbooks advising student organizations and organizers as to how to best make use of the university's resources. This series also includes student organization directories and miscellaneous publications related to campus service or leadership. Authorship reflects the numerous changes in the title of the office, as publications produced by the Student Organizations and Account Office, Student Organizations and Activities Program, Student Organization Development Center, and Student Organizational Services are all present.
  - Directory of Student Organizations / Student Organizations Directory 1990-1997 (Box 3)
  - Guide to Student Organization Services 1996-1999, 2008 (Box 3)
  - LeaderShape Directories 1997-2006, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan Leadership Award Programs 1996-2009 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Leadership Initiatives 1997, 2001, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, Booklets, and Pamphlets (Box 3)
  - Student Organization Accounts Service Reference Guide 1994 (Box 3)
  - Student Organizations Activities and Programs 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Student Organization Development Center
    - Brochures and Pamphlets 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
    - Handouts 1980s (Box 3)
  - Student Organization Handbooks (various authoring units)
    - Handbooks 1959, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Handbooks 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Handbooks 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
  - Synergy the Guide to Student Organizations and Activities, 1997-2001 (Box 3)